Bibliography of Jamestown Sources
National Park Service, Colonial Williamsburg Foundation, College of William and Mary
- Maps/Plans
  - Air Photo Compila[tion] Survey No. T-8076[?] James River, Va. Jamestown Island - Barre[ts Point?] Project No. CS 283[?] Compilation by: Ruth M. Whitson Date [?] Fred L. Peacock, Chief of [?] Baltimore Photogrammetr[?]. [Ca. 1942]., 1030
    Size: 84 x 68.5 cm. (CW copy, incomplete) Scale: 1:10,000 (16 cm. = ca. 1 mile) Shows Swann Point, Powhatan Creek and all but the eastern end of Jamestown Island (37 & deg;11'N to 37 & deg;15'N and 76 & deg;49'W to 76 & deg;45'W). Jamestown Island is separated from the mainland by Back River and The Thorofare. Areas of marsh, brush and grass are indicated, as are trees, creeks, and ponds. Church Point, Jamestown (Village), Goose Hill, and Lower Point are identified. Landmarks and topographic stations are indicated all along the waterfront, including Government Wharf and the Ferry Slip. The road onto Jamestown Island crosses a Fixed Wooden Bridge over Back River. Other roads and trails on the island are indicated. Available: CNHP, CW
  - Property to be acquired from Benson-Phillips Co. for Colonial Parkway National Park Service Yorktown, Va. July 1942., 1031
    Size: 15 x 33.5 cm. Scale: 1 in. = 500 ft. Shows a section of Back River from the bridge on route 31 to The Thoroughfare. Jamestown Island is not identified, but the part that is outlined is labeled Commonwealth of Virginia. On the mainland a section of the Colonial Parkway is charted, and two sites are labeled Old Fort. This drawing is from James City County Plat Book 9:38. It may be a reduction of the original since dimensions do not seem to match the indicated scale. Available: CW, JCC
  - U.S. Geological Survey. Virginia Yorktown Quadrangle. Surveyed in 1904 and 1905. Edition of 1907, reprinted 1944., 1032
    Size: 53 x 43 cm. Scale: 1:62,500 (1 in. = ca. 1 mile) Extends from 37 & deg;N to 37 & deg;15'N and from 76 & deg;45'W to 76 & deg;30'W. The chart shows a section of the James River from the eastern end of Jamestown Island to the mouths of the Warwick and Pagan rivers. Yorktown and Gloucester Point on the York River are indicated in the upper right corner of the sheet. Approximately one-fourth of Jamestown Island is shown, from Lower Point to Black Point at the extreme eastern end. The Thorofare separates this part of the island from the mainland. Passmore Creek is identified, and most of the eastern end of the island is shown to be marshland. The island is labeled Colonial National Historical Park, as is a strip of land along the riverbank on the mainland. Mill Creek and College Creek also are indicated on the mainland. Available: CW
  - ---. Virginia, Surry Quadrangle. Edition of 1919, reprinted 1945., 1033
    Size: 53.5 x 43 cm. Scale: 1:62,500 (1 in. = ca. 1 mile) Differs little from the 1919 printing. There are no offshore contour lines and no green shading for woodlands. Jamestown National Historic Site is indicated at the western end of Jamestown Island; the rest of the island is labeled Colonial National Historical Park. Glass House Point is indicated on the mainland at the mouth of Powhatan Creek. Available: CW
  - U.S. Coast and Geodetic Survey. Virginia James River Hog Point to Swann Point. Hydrographic Survey No. 7641 Surveyed by E. B. Latham & C. A. Schoene. June-July 1948., 1034
    Size: 102 x 162 cm. Scale: 1:10,000 (16 cm. = ca. 1 mile) Shows detailed soundings in the James River, Back River, The Thorofare, and Passmore Creek. Lower Point and Church Point are indicated on Jamestown Island. There are also numerous triangulation points and other landmarks, such as dock ruins, stakes, and snags, around the perimeter of the island. Insets show soundings in Powhatan Creek and Mill Creek. Another inset (26 x 22 cm.; scale 1:1,000) shows soundings around two wharves at Jamestown: Government Wharf and, about 200 feet to the east, Ferry Wharf. The end of Government Wharf is labeled Church Point Light. At the end of Ferry Wharf there is an area identified as ruins. Available: CNHP, CW
  - U.S. Army. Corps of Engineers. National Park Service Colonial National Historical Park Jamestown Island, Va. Proposed Roadway Crossing to Jamestown Island. File J1-1-1.1. February 1950., 1035
    Size: 76 x 107 cm. Scale: 1 in. = 200 ft. Blueprint. Oriented with east-northeast at the top. Shows Glasshouse Point and the western end of Jamestown Island with two schemes for a proposed roadway crossing. The existing road, which approached the island across Back River, is partially indicated. A Conf. fort, a monument, and the existing ferry landing are also identified. On Glasshouse Point the site of a colonial glasswork and a proposed new ferry landing are shown. The lower half of the sheet is occupied by a profile and sections of the proposed roadway. A second sheet is a copy of the original drawing, revised on February 18, 1969, to show the actual causeway as built. Available: CW
  - U.S. Geological Survey. Surry Quadrangle, Virginia: 7.5 Minute Series (Topographic). Mapped by U.S. Coast and Geodetic Survey; edited and published by the Geological Survey. Topography from aerial photographs by photogrammetric methods. Washington: 1953., 1036
    Size: 68.5 x 56 cm. Scale: 1:24,000 (6.7 cm. = 1 mile) Extends from 37 & deg;7'30"N to 37 & deg;15'N and from 76 & deg;52'30"W to 76 & deg;45'W. A section of the James River from the mouth of the Chickahominy River to Jamestown Island extends across the sheet. Approximately three-fourths of Jamestown Island is shown, from Church Point to Lower Point. The island is separated from the mainland by Back River and The Thorofare. Most of the island is shown to be about equal parts marshland and woods, with cleared land indicated only around Jamestown. Also indicated on the island are Jamestown National Historic Site, Colonial National Historical Park, ruins and a monument at Jamestown, Pyping Point, Back River Marsh, Pitch and Tar Swamp, Kingsmill Creek, Passmore Creek, Goose Hill, and earth ruins. Indicated on the mainland are Glass House Point, Powhatan Creek, sections of Lake Powell and Mill Creek, and a strip of land included in Colonial National Historical Park. Route 31, also labeled Rolfe Highway, approaches Jamestown Island through the marsh north of Back River, crosses the river onto the western end of the island, and proceeds to a ferry dock at Jamestown. The ferry connects to Scotland across the James River. The area off the northwestern tip of Jamestown Island, where Back River and Powhatan Creek enter the James River, is identified as Sandy Bay. There are depth curves and soundings in the river. Available: CW
  - U.S. Coast and Geodetic Survey. United States--East Coast Cheaspeake Bay--Virginia James River, Newport News to Jamestown Island. [No.] 529. 10th, rev. ed. Washington: The Survey, 1956., 1037
    Size: 107.5 x 90.5 cm. Scale: 1:40,000 (4 cm. = ca. 1 mile) Extends from 36 & deg;53'N to 37 & deg;14'N and from 76 & deg;47'W to 76 & deg;25'W. An inset, Continuation of Nansemond River, extends to 36 & deg;44'N at Suffolk. Jamestown Island is separated from the mainland by Back River and The Thorofare. Church Point, Jamestown, a monument, a ferry dock, Passmore Creek, Goose Hill, and Lower Point are indicated. A road approaches through the marsh north of Back River, crosses the river onto the western end of the island, and proceeds to the ferry and then across the island to the extreme eastern point (unlabeled). Green shading indicates marsh. Powhatan Creek, Mill Creek, and College Creek are indicated on the mainland. Soundings, buoys, beacons, and dangers are indicated in waterways. Goose Hill Channel is charted in the James River south and east of Jamestown Island. Available: CW
  - Hull, John. James Forte at James' Towne, A.D. 1607. [Richmond]: A. H. Robins Co., 1957., 1038
    Size: 33 x 43 cm. Oriented with north toward the upper left corner. A reproduction in the style of early seventeenth-century cartography, based on historical records of the period. Available: Cornell University
  - U.S. National Park Service. Colonial National Historical Park. Archeological Base Map of the Site of "James Towne," Jamestown Island, Virginia: Portion of Jamestown Island West of Orchard Run and South of Pitch and Tar Swamp. [1958]., 1039
    Size: 52 x 106 cm. Scale: 4.3 cm. = 100 ft. Oriented with northeast at the top. Extends from the Confederate Fort to just west of Orchard Run and from the James River to Pitch and Tar Swamp. The Ludwell-Statehouse Group is shown in an inset. The map is drawn on a grid of 100-foot squares oriented to true north. Archaeological excavations in the 1930s and 1950s are indicated. Buildings, wells, ditches, and refuse pits are depicted and numbered. This map, folded and in a pocket, accompanies John L. Cotter's Archeological Excavations at Jamestown... (ENTRY 142). Available: CNHP, CW
  - U.S. Geological Survey. Hog Island Quadrangle, Virginia: 7.5 Minute Series (Topographic). Mapped, edited, and published by the Geological Survey. Topography by photogrammetric methods from aerial photographs taken 1963. Washington: 1965., 1040
    Size: 68.5 x 56 cm. Scale: 1:24,000 (6.7 cm. = 1 mile) Extends from 37 & deg;7'30"N to 37 & deg;15'N and from 76 & deg;45'W to 76 & deg;37'30"W. The chart shows a section of the James River from the eastern end of Jamestown Island to Carter's Grove. Approximately one-fourth of Jamestown Island is shown, from Lower Point to Black Point at the extreme eastern end. The Thorofare separates this part of the island from the mainland. Passmore Creek and Travis Cemetery are also indicated. Most of this part of the island is shown to be marshland, but there is wooded area on the north side. On the mainland the Colonial National Historical Parkway runs along the shore. Mill Creek, Lake Powell, the Williamsburg-Jamestown Airport, College Creek, and Halfway Creek are also indicated. Available: CW
  - ---. Surry Quadrangle, Virginia: 7.5 Minute Series (Topographic). Mapped, edited, and published by the Geological Survey. Topography by photogrammetric methods from aerial photographs taken 1963. Washington: 1965., 1041
    Size: 68.5 x 56 cm. Scale: 1:24,000 (6.7 cm. = 1 mile) Covers the same area as the 1953 Surry chart (ENTRY 1036). Island features are very similar to those on the earlier chart. There is no ferry dock on the island, however, and a more extensive network of roads is indicated across the island. A museum, a cemetery, and a visitor center are identified at Jamestown. Most of the non-marsh area of the island is enclosed in five-foot contour lines, and two small areas are shown to be above ten feet. The road onto the island is now the Colonial National Historical Parkway, which crosses a causeway and bridge connecting Glass House Point to Church Point and separating Sandy Bay from the James River. On the mainland, route 31 has been diverted to a new ferry dock near Jamestown Festival Park, just north of Glass House Point. Available: CW
  - Dolph's Map of Williamsburg, James City County, Yorktown, York County, Virginia. Fort Lauderdale, Fla.: Dolph Map Co., 1980., 1042
    Size: 132 x 56 cm. (printed on both sides) Scale: ca. 1:39,000 (4 cm. = ca. 1 mile) Includes a schedule of the Jamestown-Scotland ferry, and a street index.
  - U.S. Geological Survey. Topographic Map of Colonial National Historical Park, Virginia, Including Jamestown, Yorktown, Williamsburg. National Park Series--Topographic. Reston, Va.: 1981., 1043
    Size: 61 x 116 cm. Scale: 1:25,000 (6 cm. = ca. 1 mile) Relief shown by contours and spot heights; depths shown by isolines and soundings. Includes notes, inset (Swanns Point area), location map, and colored illustrations; text and colored illustrations on verso.
  - U.S. National Park Service. Colonial National Historical Park, Virginia. [ACSM Map Design Competition Collection, 1981-20]. Washington: [1981?], 1044
    Size: 40 x 42 cm. Scale: ca. 1:75,000 (2 cm. = ca. 1 mile) Includes text and colored illustrations. On verso: text, maps of Jamestown National Historic Site and Yorktown Battlefield, and colored illustrations. Reprinted in 1984 and 1994.
  - U.S. Army. Corps of Engineers. Jamestown Island Seawall Repair General Plan & Location Map. File No. H-29-21-31(1). [1983?], 1045
    Size: 58 x 89 cm. Scale: 1 in. = 200 ft. Blueprint. Oriented with northeast at the top. Shows Sandy Bay and approximately one-half mile both north and south of the causeway, including all of the APVA property. Almost all of the charted area that is not a part of Jamestown Island has been crossed out, and erasures also are evident. Apparently the seawall repair plan was drawn on an amended 1954 chart. A marsh, a road, contour lines, and what appears to be a monument pedestal are all that are indicated on the APVA property. A Location Map inset (18.5 x 22 cm.) extends from Smithfield to Yorktown and from Jamestown Island to Newport News. Available: CNHP, CW
  - ---. Jamestown Island Seawall Repair Site Plan Station 0+00 to Station 8+54.40. Drawing No. 88-03-05 Sheet No. 1 Norfolk District File No. H-29-21-64.2. 6 April 1983., 1046
    Size: 76 x 107 cm. Scale: 1 in. = 30 ft. Blueprint. Oriented with northeast at the top. Shows approximately 900 feet of the riverbank beginning just west of the Dale Craft House and extending to the southeast past two granite monuments. Trees, park benches, a gravel road, elevations, and soundings are indicated. Available: CNHP, CW
  - ---. Jamestown Island Seawall Repair Site Plan Station 8+54.40 to Station 17+70.3. Drawing No. 88-03-05 Sheet No. 2 Norfolk District File No. H-29-21-64.3. 6 April 1983., 1047
    Size: 76 x 107 cm. Scale: 1 in. = 30 ft. Blueprint. Oriented with east at the top. Shows approximately 1000 feet of the riverbank extending north from the Dale Craft House. Among features indicated are brick foundations and a brick monument. Elevations and soundings are given. Available: CNHP, CW
  - Champion Map of Historical Williamsburg, Virginia, Including Jamestowne and Historical Guide Map. Rev. ed. Charlotte, N.C.: Champion Map Corporation, 1987., 1048
    Size: 49 x 64 cm. (both sides used) Includes zip codes, population information, and index.
  - James City County (Va.) Zoning Districts: James City County. [Williamsburg: 1987?], 1049
    Size: 28 x 40 in. Three maps: South County (Parkway/Skiffes Creek); Mid-County (Lightfoot/Jamestown); North County (Lanexa/Lightfoot). Available: Williamsburg Regional Library
  - Weyss, J. E. High Bridge and Farmville. New York: New York Lithographing, Engraving, and Printing Co., 1987., 1050
    Size: 54 x 75 cm. Scale: 1:20,750 (8 cm. = ca. 1 mile) Includes the river valley from the vicinity of Farmville to the vicinity of Jamestown. Relief shown pictorially. From surveys under the direction of N. Michler, by command of A.A. Humphreys, 1867. Available: Northern Illinois University
  - U.S. Coast Survey. United States--East Coast, Chesapeake Bay--Virginia, James River, Jamestown Island to Jordan Point; James River, Jordan Point to Richmond. 21st ed. Washington: The Survey, 1996., 1051
    Size: 87 x 112 cm. (both sides used) Depths shown by isolines and soundings. Relief shown by contours. Includes tidal information and a table of channel depths.
  - ---. United States--East Coast, Chesapeake Bay--Virginia, James River, Newport News to Jamestown Island. 35th ed. Washington: The Survey, 1997., 1052
    Size: 100 x 84 cm. Scale: 1:40,000 (4 cm. = ca. 1 mile) Depths shown by isolines and soundings. Relief shown by contours. Tidal information included. Insets include Back River and College Creek.
- Motion Pictures
  - An Allied View of American Heritage. U.S. Department of the Air Force, 1965. 1 reel (14 min., col.), 1053
    Shows a tour of Yorktown, Williamsburg, and Jamestown given for military officers of allied countries to provide insight into American heritage.
  - Amazing America: A Vacation into History. [Greyhound Corp., 1963]. 1 reel (13 min., col.), 1054
    Presents an elementary schoolteacher's record of her seven-day colonial tour of the Old Dominion, with historical narration. The tour includes visits to Yorktown battlefields; the College of William and Mary and the Governor's Palace in Williamsburg; and reconstructions of James Fort and the three ships at Jamestown Settlement. Narrated by Sidney Berry.
  - American Industry, Past And Present. New York: National Association of Manufacturers, Film Service Bureau, n.d. 1 reel (14 min., b & w)., 1055
    Outlines the development of American industry from Jamestown and other settlements to modern factories.
  - Arms and Defense at Jamestown. Written by W. Woodruff and G. Moore. Settling the East [series]. Ealing Corp., 1968. 1 reel (4 min., col.), 1056
    Describes the protection of the American pioneers at Jamestown, and shows how craftsmen made arms.
  - Captain John Smith, Explorer. Richmond: Virginia Department of Education, 1948., 1057
    1 reel (17 min.)Depicts the exploration of early Virginia, adventures with the Indians, and the Pocahontas story as told by the 'voice' of John Smith's statue in Jamestown.
  - Captain John Smith, Founder of Virginia. Produced by John Barnes. Encyclopaedia Britannica Films, 1954. 1 reel (20 min., b & w), with a teacher's guide., 1058
    Follows the career of John Smith, whose influence and leadership contributed to the establishment of the English colony at Jamestown in 1607. Traces the events in England which preceded the colonists' voyage to Virginia, and shows the natural and human obstacles faced by Smith in his efforts to launch the settlement.
  - Common Law. Richmond: Virginia Department of Education, 1961. 1 reel (13 min., col.), 1059
    Traces the history of common law in the United States from its establishment at Jamestown in 1607 to modern times. Relates common law to our contemporary lives and our democratic freedoms.
  - [Documentary film of the Jamestown Festival]. Richmond: WRVA-TV, [1957?], 1060
    Selected footage taken before and during the Festival.Edited by Richard L. Speers.
  - First Houses at Jamestown. Written by W. Woodruff and G. Moore. Settling the East [series]. Ealing Corp., 1968. 1 reel (4 min., col.), 1061
    Shows craftsmen at work building the first houses of Jamestown.
  - The Founding of Jamestown. New York: National Council of the Protestant Episcopal Church, Audio Visual Division, [1957?] 1 reel (17.5 min., col.), 1062
  - International Naval Review. Washington: U.S. Navy Department, 1959. 1 reel (11 min., col.), 1063
    A documentary of the naval review during the 1957 Jamestown Festival in which eighteen nations participated with aircraft, 100 ships, and 12,000 men. The theme of the review was "Freedom of the Seas."
  - Jamestown. Directed by Philip Young. Washington: National Park Service, Division of Audiovisual Arts, 1975. 1 reel (14 min., col.), 1064
    Presents the story of Jamestown from its founding until the early eighteenth century. (See ENTRY 1080 for the videocassette version of this film.)
  - Jamestown, a Place of Beginnings. Richmond: Virginia State Board of Education, Film Production Service, 1958. 1 reel (21 min., b & w)., 1065
    Describes the history of Jamestown from its beginnings in 1607 through its ninety years of prominence.
  - The Jamestown Colony (1607 through 1620). Chicago: Coronet Instructional Films, 1957. 1 reel (16 min., col.), with a teacher's guide., 1066
    Records the early history of Jamestown through reconstructions at the Jamestown Festival of 1957, showing the voyage of the first settlers from England, and emphasizing the faith and dedication required of them and later arrivals in overcoming hardships in America and in permanently establishing their colonyAlso produced on videocassette.
  - Jamestown Exposition International Naval Review, Hampton Roads, Va. [Thomas A. Edison, Inc., 1907]. George Kleine Collection, Library of Congress. 1 reel (154 ft., b & w)., 1067
    Footage of the international naval review of 1907 during the 300th anniversary of the founding of Jamestown, showing some of the decorated battleships (including the US Indiana), cruisers, torpedo boats, destroyers, and monitors from the United States and several other nations, as they pass in review before President Theodore Roosevelt (not pictured) on his yacht, the Mayflower, in the Hampton Roads harbor. Probably filmed from a moving boat.
  - Jamestown, the First English Settlement in America. Chicago: Encyclopaedia Britannica Films, 1958. 1 reel (22 min.), with a teacher's guide., 1068
    Tells how the Jamestown colony found economic prosperity in tobacco planting. Uses John Rolfe as the central character in dramatizing the struggle between the aspirations of the colonists for self-government and the need for a strong central government during the early years. Shows the development of plantations in the Jamestown settlement and the creation of the first legislative body in the New World. Photographed in and near the reconstructed Jamestown fort. Released later as a videorecording (ENTRY 1083).
  - Jamestown-Williamsburg-Yorktown. Washington: National Republican Congressional Committee, [1957?] 1 reel (25 min., col.), 1069
  - Life in the Jamestown Colony. Living in Early America, no. 1. Chicago: Coronet Instructional Films, 1967. 1 cartridge (4 min., col., with captions)., 1070
    Portrays the establishment of the first permanent English colony in America.
  - Museums of Industry and Science. Produced by Arthur Lodge Productions, Inc. Directed by Roger A. Young, Jr. Industry on Parade, no. 380. New York: National Association of Manufacturers, 1957. 1 reel (13.5 min., b & w)., 1071
    From a weekly documentary series devoted to American industry. This episode looks at historic sites, museums, factories, industrial plants and other places where visitors may view manufacturing processes or objects used in manufacturing or industry. It includes footage of an apothecary shop in Colonial Williamsburg and glassblowing in Jamestown.
  - Pocahontas. Produced by James Pentecost. Directed by Mike Gabriel and Eric Goldberg. Walt Disney Pictures (Buena Vista Pictures Distribution), 1995. 10 reels (ca. 7830 ft., col.)., 1072
    An animated and highly fictionalized treatment of the relationship between Pocahontas and John Smith. Written by Carl Binder, Susannah Grant, and Philip LaZebnik; music and original score by Alan Menken; lyrics by Stephen Schwartz; art direction by Michael Giaimo.
  - Tom Savage, Boy of Early Virginia. Chicago: Encyclopaedia Britannica Films, 1958. 1 reel (22 min.), with a teacher's guide., 1073
    The adventures of a 13-year-old boy who is given to the Indians by the Jamestown settlers as a token of friendship. Pocahontas and the young braves of Powhatan's household help the boy learn the language, skills, and customs of the tribe, a knowledge which he later uses to serve the Virginia colony.Photographed in and near the reconstructed Jamestown fort.
  - A Vacation into History. Virginia Department of Conservation and Economic Development, 1963. 1 reel (13 min., col.), 1074
    Presents a vacation trip to historic attractions in Virginia and Washington, D.C. Places visited include Jamestown, Williamsburg, Yorktown, and James River plantations.
  - Williamsburg in the American Heritage. Williamsburg: Colonial Williamsburg, Inc., n.d. 1 reel (19 min., col.), 1075
    Traces the years across Virginia's historic peninsula from the landing at Jamestown to victory at Yorktown. Uses maps, old prints, historic paintings, and color photographs to view people, places, and events important to America's heritage.
- Videorecordings
  - The Battle of Yorktown. Produced by Henri de Turenne and Daniel Costelle. Directed by Aimee Danis. Turning Points in History [series]. Princeton, N.J.: Films for the Humanities, 1991. 1 videocassette (col.), 1076